哟！　　　李爷来啦
Master Li is here!
李爷来啦
秀莲
Shu Lien!
秀莲，李慕白来啦
Shu Lien! Li Mu Bai is here!
李爷
家里好吗？　　　 挺好的
How's everything? Fine. Please come in.
请进
慕白兄，好久不见
Mu Bai, it's been too long.
是啊！镖局的生意怎么样？
It has. How's business?
还行，你好吗？
Good. And how are you?
好
Fine.
道元真人，年初从武当山路过这里
Monk Zheng said you were at Wudan Mountain.
说起你正在闭关修练
He said you were practicing deep meditation.
嗯
山上是清静
The mountain must be so peaceful...
有时候我真羡慕你
I envy you.
我光是忙着镖局的生意，静不下来
My work keeps me so busy, I hardly get any rest.
我破了戒，提早出关
I left the training early.
为什么？
Why?
道人说这次的闭关对你非常重要
You're a Wudan fighter. Training is everything.
这次闭关静坐的时候
During my meditation training...
我一度进入了一种很深的寂静
I came to a place of deep silence...
我的周围只有光
I was surrounded by light...
时间、空间都不存在了
Time and space disappeared.
我似乎触到了…
I had come to a place...
师父从未指点过的境地
my master had never told me about.
你得道了？
You were enlightened?
我没有这种感觉
No.
因为我并没有得道的喜悦
I didn't feel the bliss of enlightenment.
相反的…
Instead...
却被一种寂灭的悲哀环绕
I was surrounded by an endless sorrow.
这悲哀超过了我能承受的极限
I couldn't bear it.
我出了定，没办法再继续
I broke off my meditation. I couldn't go on.
有些事…我需要想想
There was something... pulling me back.
什么事？
What was it?
一些心里放不下的事
Something I can't let go of.
你要出门了吗？
You're leaving soon?
有一趟镖要到北京
We're preparing a convoy for a delivery
已经收拾好了，就要上路
to Peking.
有件东西…
Perhaps I could ask you
烦劳你替我带给贝勒爷
to deliver something to Sir Te for me.
青冥剑！把它送给贝勒爷？
The Green Destiny sword? You're giving it to Sir Te?
是啊
I am.
贝勒爷一直是最关心我们的人
He has always been our greatest protector.
我还是不明白
I don't understand.
这是你随身的佩剑
How can you part with it?
这么多年，它一直都跟着你
It has always been with you.
跟着我惹来不少的江湖恩怨
Too many men have died at its edge.
你看它干干净净的
It only looks pure...
因为它杀人不沾血
because blood washes so easily from its blade.
你不是个滥杀无辜的人
You use it justly,
所以你才配用这把剑
you're worthy of it.
该是离开这些恩怨的时候了
It's time for me to leave it behind.
离开？
之后呢？
So what will you do now?
干脆和我一起去北京
Come with me to Peking.
我觉得你应该亲手把剑交给贝勒爷
You can give the sword to Sir Te yourself.
记得我们以前经常结伴去北京吗？
It'll be just like old times.
我这趟下山，想先去给恩师扫墓
First I must visit my master's grave.
恩师遭碧眼狐狸暗算…
It's been many years since Jade Fox murdered him.
这么多年了，师仇还没报
I have yet to avenge his death.
我竟然萌生了退出江湖的念头
And yet I'm thinking of quitting.
我想我该去求他的原谅
I must pray for his forgiveness.
既然是这样
办完了事，你到北京跟我会合
Join me once you have finished.
你来，我就等你
I can wait for you in Peking.
也许吧
Perhaps.
可以了
Ok. Pass.
各位爷，谢了
Thanks.
进城，交了货歇着
Let's go into the city.
进城！
谢天谢地，俞姑娘辛苦了
Everything got here safely. I'm much obliged.
哪儿的话
人货平安是我们跑镖应该的
Just doing my job.
“雄远镖局”的招牌…
Sun Security has been the best...
打俞师父起就从来没有砸过
since your father started it.
您押了这几趟
您父亲的在天之灵应该放心了
You're a credit to his memory.
那可不敢说
Thank you.
是怎么回事，就怎么回事
I mean it.
这是慕白的贴身佩剑
This is Li Mu Bai's personal sword,
宝剑佩英雄
a great hero's weapon.
当今天下
He is the only one...
论剑法、论武德
in the world...
只有慕白配使用这把剑
worthy of carrying it.
礼太重，我不能收
It's too fine a gift. I cannot accept it.
贝勒爷
Sir Te...
这把剑惹了无数江湖恩怨
it has brought him as much trouble as glory.
慕白说，他要从此离开这些恩怨
Help him to leave these troubles behind.
您不收下，恩怨不了
Otherwise, he'll never be able to start anew.
嗯，也是，我就替他管着吧
All right. I'll act as the sword's custodian.
九门提督府玉大人到
Governor Yu has arrived.
更衣
I must change.
是
多谢贝勒爷…
一直关照我和慕白的事
You've always been so good to Li Mu Bai and me.
我不该多打扰，晚辈告辞了
Please accept our thanks.
别急着走
Please do not be such a stranger.
你不是外人，在这儿住下
You'll stay the night as my guest.
秀莲啊！告诉我一件事
Now, Shu Lien, tell me something.
可别怪我多事
And forgive me for prying.
就因为你的爹是我的好友
Your father was a great friend to me,
我一直把你当成自己的女儿看待
and I think of you as my own daughter.
贝勒爷有什么话，请尽管说
Please, Sir Te, what is it?
李慕白突然交出青冥剑
Li Mu Bai giving up his sword
又退出了江湖…
and his warrior days...
莫非他向你暗示些什么
Maybe he's trying to tell you something?
我不知道
I don't know...
不要害羞
Don't be coy.
你们的感情我是知道的
I've always known about your feelings for each other.
只是你们太小心翼翼
All these years, it's a shame...
总是不敢向对方承认这份感情
...neither of you is brave enough to admit the truth to the other.
白白的浪费多年的光阴
You're both wasting precious time.
我跟慕白都不是胆怯的人
I beg your pardon.
也许事情并不是您想的那样
Li Mu Bai and I aren't cowards.
面对情字
When it comes to emotions,
再大的英雄也是莫可奈何呀
even great heroes can be idiots.
下回遇了他，他要是再不肯明讲
Tell me if Li Mu Bai is not more open the next time you see him.
告诉我，我去跟他说
I'll give him an earful!
贝勒爷说，就搁在这屋里
Sir Te said to leave the sword in here.
您…
Who are you?
我是府上今儿的客
I'm your guest today.
是玉府的小姐
I am Governor Yu's daughter.
这是贝勒爷的书斋，姑娘您…
This is Sir Te's study. You are here to?
外头人多我头昏
I was just...
想找个清静的地方透口气儿
looking for a quiet corner.
小的是铁府管事得禄
I am Sir Te's head servant.
这也是贝勒爷的客
And this is another of our guests.
这么沉？剑不就是片薄铁吗？
It's heavy for such a thin piece of metal!
沉的是剑柄，剑身倒也不是薄铁
The handle is heavy. And the blade is no ordinary metal.
剑走轻灵，兵器里它算是最轻的
Still, the sword is the lightest of weapons.
你没摸过兵器就觉得它沉
You're just not used to handling it.
谁说我没摸过兵器，摸过的
But, I have had much practice.
我爹在新疆，家里养有府兵
As a child in the West, a platoon lived with us.
能摸他们的兵器，也玩儿
They'd let me play with their weapons.
这剑套真好看
The scabbard is so beautiful.
再好看也是凶器
Beautiful but dangerous.
刃上染了血
Once you see it tainted with blood,
你就不会说它好看了
its beauty is hard to admire.
这把剑有四百年的来历
It's 400 years old.
真好看
Exquisite!
你刚才说这把剑是归…
You said it belongs to...
原本是我恩兄李慕白的
My friend Li Mu Bai.
现在他送给了贝勒爷
He's given it to Sir Te as a gift.
李慕白？我在新疆都听说过他
Li Mu Bai!
大名鼎鼎的
The famous warrior?
可他为什么把这把剑…
Why would he give his sword...
给了贝勒爷呢
to Sir Te?
说多了你也不懂
You're too young to understand.
俞姐是使剑的吧
You're a sword fighter too?
我使双刀，剑法我略懂一二
Yes, I am. But I prefer the machete.
李慕白的武当玄牝剑法
Certain moves,
真是得用这把剑才行啊
however, call for a sword.
是吧
Really?
你在江湖上走来走去的…
It must be exciting to be a fighter,
是不是很好玩？
to be totally free!
走江湖…
Fighters have rules too:
靠的是人熟，讲信、讲义
friendship, trust,
应下来的，就要做到
integrity... Without rules,
不讲信义，可就玩不长了
we wouldn't survive for long.
可我看书上说的…
I've read all about...
都是挺有意思的
people like you.
到处都能去，遇上不服气的就打
Roaming wild, beating up anyone who gets in your way!
写书的不那么写
Writers wouldn't sell many books...
书就没法子卖了
if they told how it really is.
我看你就象书里的人
But you're just like the characters in the stories.
洗不上澡
Sure. No place to bathe for days,
虱子跳蚤咬得睡不着觉
sleeping in flea-infested beds...
书里也写这个？
They tell you all about that in those books?
你知道我说的是什么
You know what I mean.
我就要嫁人了
I'm getting married soon,
可还没过过我自己想过的日子
but I haven't lived the life I want.
我听人说起过，恭喜了
So I heard. Congratulations.
嫁人是大事
It's the most important step...
女人一辈子，总是要嫁人的
in a woman's life, isn't it?
俞姐，还没嫁人吧？
You're not married, are you?
你看呢？
What do you think?
没有，嫁了人还能跑来跑去的？
No! You couldn't roam around freely if you were.
说你不懂事吧，又懂点事
You're probably right.
玉大人，看看
Go ahead, Governor Yu.
长二尺九，宽一寸一
2 feet 9 inches long. 1 inch wide.
护手一寸，宽二寸六，厚七分
The handle is 1 inch deep, 2.6 inches wide.\n7 tenths of an inch thick.
两耳各一寸五
剑柄原镶有七星
With seven rubies missing from the hilt.
从剑的旋纹看…
You can tell the design
是先秦吴国的揉剑法
dates back to before the Chin era.
到汉朝就失传了
Engraved with a technique lost by the time of the Han Dynasty.
贝勒爷真是博古通今哪
Your knowledge is remarkable, Sir Te.
剑要人用才能活
A sword by itself rules nothing.
所谓剑法即人法
It comes alive only through skillful manipulation.
卑职愿闻其详
I see your point. Please continue.
这京城内城…还好说
The Imperial Court isn't the problem.
无非是皇亲国戚
With royalty and officials everywhere,
各部的官员，加之八旗军…
the Royal Guard...
布防严密，各有辖区
keeps security tight.
这外城就杂了
But Peking is not like the West.
三教九流，往来人等
Here, you'll find all sorts of characters.
玉大人整治京畿
Proceed with caution in your quest for law and order.
不能只眼看着朝廷
Don't depend only on the court.
江湖上…也要有所联络
Contacts in the Giang Hu underworld
九门提督才坐得稳
can ensure your position.
刚柔相济，方得治道
Be strong yet supple. This is the way to rule.
高师娘
Governess...
我来好了
Let me do it.
师娘坐
Please sit.
做了两件睡衣，丝料的
I've made you silk pajamas.
要不要换上？
Do you want to change into them?
放着吧
Put them down.
听说你见到俞秀莲了？
I heard you met Shu Lien today.
你知道她？
Do you know her?
听说她是道上的人
She's one of those.
夫人不会让你跟那路人混吧
Your mother would not want you consorting with her kind.
我愿意跟谁混就跟谁混
I'll socialize with whomever I please.
麻烦进了家，就真麻烦
Don't invite danger into your father's house.
我困了
I'm tired now!
那就睡吧
Go to bed then.
小姐长大了，要嫁人了
Miss has grown up, and is getting married soon.
以后真不知道会怎么样
God knows what the future will bring.
还不是一样
It'll be just the same.
好了吧？我困了
Enough! I'm tired.
立秋了，我去帮你把窗子关好
Autumn is coming. I'll shut the windows for you.
天冷了
Chilly, eh?
刘师傅
Yes, Master Bo.
来人啊
Someone help!
快来！有贼
Stop him!
上房顶了
He's on the roof!
有人偷宝剑啦！
The sword's been stolen!
上房顶了
抓贼！快，抓贼！
Stop thief!
快搬梯子
有贼呀
看看有没有在房顶上？
抓住他…给我剥了狐狸皮
Stop him! It's Jade Fox!
给我抓住他
我给娘报仇
We must avenge Mother!
你们还站在这儿干什么，快追啊！
Do something! He's getting away!
宝剑物归原主，现在话还好说
Return the sword and I'll let you go.
你是武当派的门人？
You've been trained at Wudan?
我们是从外地来卖艺的
你弄错了
You're mistaken.
我正带着闺女练功呢，走吧！
We're just street performers. We were rehearsing.
爹
Father!
练功？你以为我也是在练功的？
You were rehearsing? Who are you trying to fool?
人哪儿去了
Where did that thief go?
九门提督府？
Governor Yu's house!
给我下来
Get down here!
下来
Get down!
剑给我
Give back the sword!
贝勒爷在厅里候着哪
Sir Te awaits you.
青冥剑是没找回来
可我敢赌…
I'm sure...
贼人与玉大人家有瓜葛
the thief is in the Yu household.
查他个底儿掉
放肆
How dare you imply?
可我明明见着…退下
Enough!
玉大人看过青冥剑吗？
Has Governor Yu ever seen the sword?
看过
Yes,
我想跟玉大人没有关系
though I doubt he's involved in this.
可是剑现在应该在玉府
But the sword could be in his compound.
有人要陷害玉大人
Then someone's trying to set him up.
这不是不可能的事情
这件事应该让慕白知道
We should inform Li Mu Bai.
夫人您小心啊
怎么啦？　　　玉夫人…
What is it?      Madam Yu,
有人在墙上乱贴东西
someone's put up posters.
给我看看
Let me see.
（通缉，碧眼狐狸就在玉府）
是谁跟这碧眼狐狸有仇啊…
Someone is after a Jade Fox.
放肆到府上来了
Preposterous, looking for her here!
说的是天下第一枪…
还是杨家枪
说的是第一枪…
还是我亲爹您哪！
快说
大爷，我是真是不知道啊
Where are they? I don't know.
…许是离开了吧
前两天还见着她呢
I haven't seen them in two days.
小姐，外头有位俞秀莲小姐求见
There's a Miss Shu Lien here to see you.
小姐正没空呢
Miss is busy right now.
那就回了她
I'll tell her.
请俞姑娘进来
Show her in.
是
小姐，麻烦真是进了家了
This spells trouble.
我有客
I have a guest.
俞小姐请
This way please.
俞姐姐，你想死我了
I've missed you.
想我干嘛
How so?
没事干呗
I'm bored...
练字啊
You're doing calligraphy?
我写俞姐姐的名字…练着玩儿
I'll write your name. Just for fun.
这“俞”写起来真象“剑”
I never realized my name looks like "sword".
我看你转手腕
You write gracefully.
书法剑法，道理好象是相通的
Calligraphy is so similar to fencing.
大概是吧！我不知道
Maybe it is. I wouldn't know.
请
Please.
谢谢你抽空见我
Thank you for seeing me.
听说你大喜的日子快到了
I hear your wedding day is near.
想必正为这件事忙着吧
You must be overwhelmed by the preparations.
才不呢能，不想它最好
I'm hardly doing a thing.
我什么也不愿意管
The less I think of it the better.
反正婚事由我爹娘决定
My parents are arranging everything.
他们一到京城
就替我定下这门亲事
他们说鲁老太爷是朝内的大官
The Gous are a very powerful family.
又是三代翰林
如果能跟鲁家联姻
My marrying one will be good...
对爹在北京大有好处
for my father's career.
能跟这样的名门望族结亲
You are fortunate...
这是福气
to marry into such a noble family.
是吗？
Am I?
我倒是喜欢象那些…
I wish I were like...
侠义小说里的英雄儿女
the heroes in the books I read.
就好象你和李慕白一样
Like you and Li Mu Bai.
结婚固然是喜事
I guess I'm happy to be marrying.
要是能够自由自在的生活
But to be free to live my own life,
选择自己心爱的人
to choose whom I love...
用自己的方式去爱他
那才算得上是真正的幸福
That is true happiness.
那…我给你讲个故事
Do you think so? Let me tell you a story...
是你和李慕白的事儿？
About you and Li Mu Bai?
是吧
Yes.
我小时候家里也给定过亲
Did you know I was once engaged to be married?
是吗？
No, really?
他的名字叫孟思昭
His name was Meng Si Zhao.
他跟李慕白也是拜把的兄弟
He was a brother to Li Mu Bai by oath.
有一回，在一场打斗里
One day, while in battle,
孟思昭为了救李慕白
he was killed by the sword
死在对手的刀下
of Li Mu Bai's enemy.
这之后…
After,
我们虽然又共同经历了许多事
Li Mu Bai and I went through a lot together.
感情…也日渐深厚
Our feelings for each other grew stronger.
可是我们都坚持要对得起思昭…
But how could we dishonor
和那一纸婚约
Meng's memory?
你说的自由自在，我也渴望
So the freedom you talk about, I too desire it.
但我从来没有尝过
But I have never tasted it.
可是你和李慕白谁也没有错啊
Too bad for Meng, but it's not your fault, or Li Mu Bai's.
只怪那位孟大侠福薄
爱就爱了呗
我虽然不是出身于…
I am not an aristocrat,
你们这样的官宦人家
as you are...
可是一个女人一生该服从的…
but I must still respect...
道德和礼教并不少于你们
a woman's duties.
别说你们我们
Don't distance us.
我要认你这个姐姐
From now on, let's be like sisters.
以后你跟我说话…
不许再这么见外了
好，既然作你的姐姐
Then as a sister,
就希望你真的得到幸福
let me wish you happiness in your marriage.
千里迢迢啊！千里迢迢
What a godforsaken place!
你爹这回调到伊梨
Can't your father be appointed...
还是出不了新疆，这地方…
closer to civilization?
娇龙…你听着了吗？
Jen...are you listening to me?
走吧
Let's go.
你是谁？在干嘛　　　爹
Who are you?
别…您别拿朋友当外人
Wait! I'm a friend!
对那把剑…
I...
我们父女俩一点儿也不上心
don't care about your sword.
那你们盯着玉府干嘛
Why were you spying on the Yus?
我是找个人…碧眼狐狸
I'm looking for someone. Jade Fox.
刘爷
不瞒您说，我是陕甘的总捕头
I'm a police inspector from Shaan Xi, Gen Su district.
这碧眼狐狸犯了好几桩案子
Jade Fox is a master criminal.
听说混进了玉府
I hear she infiltrated the Yus.
玉大人从新疆调北京
She must have come with them...
这碧眼狐狸一定跟着过来
when they transferred here.
碍着玉大人的面，又不能明拿
But with Yu's reputation, I can't just go in and accuse her.
只有想办法把她引出来
这碧眼狐狸是公的还是母的？
This Jade Fox is a woman?
母的
Yes.
母的就交给我了
Then leave her to me.
蔡爷，您就别操心了
得罪了，刘爷，您真的拿不住她
Pardon me, but I doubt you can handle her.
我内人也是武行中有名有姓的
My wife was quite a martial arts expert.
都被她害了
Jade Fox killed her.
刘爷，您歇着
So you see,
于公于私，这都是我的事
this is personal. Leave her to me.
丸子熟了
It's ready.
该熟的都熟了
I'm ready for anything!
不行！爹先
Father gets first dip.
走啦
They're gone!
写着什么？
What does it say?
今晚酉时黄土岗上，一决生死！
"We'll settle this at midnight on Yellow Hill."
好，狐狸出洞了
Good! The fox is out of her hole!
请
秀莲，你看谁来了
Shu Lien, look who's here.
贝勒爷觉得这样把嫌疑…
Sir Te believes it's a ploy...
贸然指向玉府，十分不妥
to cast suspicion on Governor Yu.
但玉府里确实有些蹊跷
But something is going on at the Yu household.
我得彻底弄清楚
你发现了什么？
What have you discovered?
碧眼狐狸？不可能
Jade Fox? Impossible!
你早就怀疑她逃去了西域
You'd always suspected she'd fled to the West.
可是没有想到她藏身在北京
I didn't think she'd dare come back to Peking!
有什么比逗留在玉大人府里…
Is there any place...
更安全的
safer than under the nose of Governor Yu?
师父的仇终于可以报了
So I shall avenge my master's death after all.
慕白，还是谨慎一点
Be careful.
这事贝勒爷不许声张…
Sir Te requires discretion.
原本只是公事公办都已经难了
Official business is difficult enough.
再加上你的私仇
Don't let personal...
岂不是会闹得一团糟
feelings make it worse.
再说，这张贴纸也不见得可信
And I don't know... even this poster...
难说不是个圈套
could be some sort of trap.
你看见是谁贴了吗？
Did you see who posted it?
没见着
No.
上面明指碧眼狐狸在玉府
It says Fox is hiding at Yu's.
铁爷说，丢失宝剑那天晚上
On the night of the theft...
玉府附近有打斗
there was a brawl near Yu's.
当时你在场吗？
Were you involved?
我…没有
It was Bo, Sir Te's man.
听说是护院刘泰保…
I hear he...
一路追他追到玉府
followed the thief to the Yus'.
你查问过他没有？
Have you questioned him yet?
刘泰保啊？还没有…
No, not yet...
你也没有布置镖师盯住玉府？
But your men are watching over Yu's compound?
我早就差他们回去了
No, I'd already sent them home.
宝剑失窃的事，你尽可以怪罪我
You can blame me for losing the sword,
但是请你相信，我有我的法子
but please trust that I'll get it back soon
很快给你找回来
using my own methods.
你误会我的意思
That's not what I meant.
我并不在乎这把宝剑
I don't care about the sword.
你专程赶来北京处理这件事
What do you mean?
怎么能说是不在乎？
Didn't you come back here for it?
我来北京以前
I didn't know it was stolen...
并不知道宝剑失窃的事
until I got here.
那你来是…
Then, why did you come?
我以为我们…已经讲好了嘛
Well, we had talked...
打搅二位
Pardon my intrusion. Master Li,
李爷，您房间收拾好了
your room is ready.
多谢
Thank you.
请得总管带路
Please, lead the way.
说来，就得守信哪
The Fox doesn't care much for punctuality.
怎么还闻不到骚味儿？
Still no sign of her.
好啦！不要再装啦
Enough! Show yourself!
蔡九，你这臭当差的
Tsai...You dog!
你不给我活路，我也不让你活
You will pay for your stubbornness!
嘿，你这个老太太
That's what you think,
怎么张口就骂人哪？
old witch!
要是你束手就擒
If you surrender now,
也算你走了一次正道
you'll suffer less.
否则的话，我今天就销了你的案
But if you resist, I won't stop until you're dead.
爹，我要给我娘报仇
Father! Let me avenge my mother's death!
小婊子！一起来送死
You'll soon end up like her, you little whore!
你这个老狐狸
老成这样了还嘴硬
You'll pay for that!
爹
你这老狐狸，害得我家破人亡
我今天杀了你…
小心她的点穴
She's going to paralyze you!
香妹
May!
蔡老狗
Tsai, you filthy mongrel!
你们还有个打埋伏的
An ambush!
爹…您没事吧，没事
Father, are you all right?
武当派早该铲除你这个妖孽
Wudan should have gotten rid of you long ago.
久违了，碧眼狐狸
It's been a long time, Jade Fox!
你也许不记得我李慕白
You don't remember me...
不过，你一定不会忘记…
But you should remember...
我师父江南鹤吧
my master.
当年我在九华山…闭关练剑
You infiltrated Wudan while I was away.
你冒充道姑，潜入武当
You stole our secret manual
盗走心诀，毒害我师父
and poisoned our master!
今天该是你偿还…
Now it's time...
这一段师门血债的时候了
for you to pay!
你师父可惜太小看女人
Your master underestimated us women.
即使入了房纬
Sure, he'd sleep with me,
也不肯把功夫传给我
but he would never teach me.
叫他死在女人手里
He deserved to die...
一点也不冤枉
by a woman's hand!
你盗取武当绝学，十年练剑
You stole the secrets of Wudan's highest martial arts.
只练得一身走火入魔的邪招
But after ten years of training your moves are still undisciplined.
今天教你命送武当宗门剑法之下
And today, under a Wudan sword...
对你，也不冤枉
you will die!
徒弟，来，该杀的都在这儿了
Disciple, we'll kill them all!
快走
Let's go!
狐狸还有徒弟？
Another one!
不行！我得除掉那老蔡狗
I must get rid of Tsai!
走
你是谁？
Who are you?
青冥剑为什么在你手里？
Why is the Green Destiny in your possession?
你管得着吗？
What's it to you?
在下李慕白
My name is Li Mu Bai.
青冥剑是我的剑
The Green Destiny is mine.
碧眼狐狸绝对不是你师父
Jade Fox can't be your master.
你这“玄牝剑法”从哪里学来的？
Where did you learn that "Xuan Piu" move?
随便玩玩
I'm just playing around.
你师父是谁？
Tell me, who is your master?
小婊子！你给我死
爹
快走，我要斩草除根
Let's go! We must kill them!
快走！别跟他打
走，快走
爹
Father!
这就是蔡九
This is Tsai?
我爹，陕甘捕头，蔡九
My father. Police inspector from Shaan.
按说京师命案…
This should be reported...
应该由九门提督来处置
to Governor Yu.
死者又是官差
The victim is an officer.
你确定杀人者就在玉府？
You believe the killer is hiding out in his compound?
我拿性命担保
I'd bet my life on it!
你们随我来
Come with me.
这件事情得尽快的解决
This needs to be resolved, and quickly.
玉府那里我去办
I'll get into the Yu household...
一定要查个水落石出
and get her.
让碧眼狐狸跟她的同党…
I'll ferret out Fox...
都现出原形
and her gang.
太莽撞了
We must be careful.
玉大人是朝廷的命官
Yu is a court official,
又掌管京城的治安
and in charge of security.
这件事足以毁掉…
Any disturbance will...
玉大人一生的清誉
cast suspicion on him.
也会让贝勒爷陷入两难的局面
It might get Sir Te in trouble.
这事难办
This is a delicate matter.
贝勒爷，您能不能找个什么借口…
Sir Te, can you find some excuse
把玉夫人和玉小姐…
to invite...
请到府里来坐坐？
Madam Yu and her daughter?
哦？你是打算…
What do you have in mind?
要抓老狐狸，最好从小狐狸着手
The best way to trap a fox is through her cubs.
哎呀，真过意不去
买了料子还要我们挑
到底是福晋
Madam Te is certainly spoiling us with these wedding gifts.
我们嫁闺女，可让你们费心了
She's being so considerate.
福晋这两天着了点凉
I'm sorry she's not feeling well...
陪不了你们
enough to receive you today.
听说贝勒府上丢东西了
I heard Sir Te lost something.
真是的，福晋身体又不合适
And now Madam Te's not feeling well...
丢的东西，已经知道是谁拿了
We know who stole the missing item.
其实拿了剑的人
If the thief...
能自己把剑放回去
returns it,
贝勒爷给面子，也就不追究了
I'm sure Sir Te will pursue the matter no further.
那就好了
That's good.
有时候，这下人手脚不干净
Sometimes the help can't keep their hands to themselves.
也是挺烦人的
It's very embarrassing.
贝勒爷的意思是…
Sir Te knows that
再好的人也有犯错的时候
even well-meaning people can make mistakes...
有的错误不仅是害了自己
that can bring ruin to themselves...
还连累了全家人
and their families.
有时候这心也不能太软
But don't be too lenient.
是啊
好比说最近这里出了个杀人的
No mercy will be shown toward the murderer
贝勒爷就绝对饶不过他
who turned up in Peking.
城里也会出这种事？
A murderer?
可不是
Yes,
凶手就是当年毒害…
the very killer of...
我恩兄李慕白师父的女贼
Li Mu Bai's own master.
昨儿夜里把一个…
Last night,
追捕她好多年的捕头给杀了
she killed a policeman who had tracked her down.
女贼有这么大的本事，那倒新鲜
A female criminal! Now that's news!
怎么？你说她杀的是个官差？
You say she killed a policeman?
是位陕甘的名捕
Yes, from the West.
化装成江湖卖艺的
He went undercover,
一路跟上北京城里来的
and followed her here.
唉，我瞎说啊
Maybe the murderer
偷剑杀人会不会是同一个人？
and the thief are the same.
应该是不至于
I doubt that.
这个盗剑人…很不寻常
This thief...is very unusual.
应该不会这么傻的
And most likely smarter than a mere killer.
娇龙给贝勒爷请安
Greetings, Sir Te.
好…
玉夫人安好
Hello, Madam Yu.
这位是李慕白，有名的侠士
This is Li Mu Bai, the renowned swordsman.
玉夫人、玉小姐，幸会
Delighted to meet you.
玉小姐就要出阁了
Miss Yu is soon to be married.
福气，福气
Congratulations.
来了怎么不进来呢
Why don't you come in?
给你守个门
I'm standing guard.
外头冷，进屋里来吧
Come in. It's cold.
进来吧
Come in.
两个人就不怕打不过碧眼狐狸了
We don't have to fear Jade Fox if we're together.
这么晚了，还不歇着？
Isn't it a bit late to be out?
来还剑吗？
You've brought me the sword?
高兴就还，不高兴就不还
I do as I please.
你师父在哪？
Where is your master?
你管不着
What's it to you?
飞够了？
Had enough flying?
天份不错
You've got potential.
只不过你们对武当心诀的领略…
You've studied the Wudan manual...
理路不正
but you don't understand it.
你需要良师的调教，重理剑法
You need a real master.
想当我师父？
Do you think you are a real master?
谁知道你是不是浪得虚名
“李慕白”就是虚名
Like most things, I am nothing.
宗派是虚名，剑法也是虚名
这把青冥剑还是虚名
It's the same for this sword.
一切都是人心的作用
All of it is simply a state of mind.
别到了庙里就说和尚的话，出招！
Stop talking like a monk! Just fight!
那就快告诉我，碧眼狐狸在哪里
Then tell me where Jade Fox is.
看招！
On guard!
揣而锐之，不可长保
Real sharpness comes without effort.
勿助、勿长
No growth. Without assistance.
不应、不辩
No action. Without reaction.
无知无欲
No desire without restraint.
“舍己从人”才能“我顺人背”
Now give yourself up and find yourself again.
教你一点做人处事的道理
There is a lesson for you.
下手吧
Go ahead.
何必？
Why should I?
你还要修练，修武德
You need practice.
才能体会静中之动的境界
I can teach you to fight with the Green Destiny,
才配得上用这把青冥剑
but first you must learn to hold it in stillness.
你为什么要教我？
Why do you want to teach me?
我一直在想找一个徒弟
I've always wanted a disciple
能把武当派的“玄牝剑法”传下去
worthy of Wudan's secrets.
你不怕我学会了杀了你
And if I use them to kill you?
即为师徒，就要以性命相见
That's a risk I'm willing to take.
我相信
Deep down, you're good.
碧眼狐狸未能泯灭了你的良心
Even Jade Fox couldn't corrupt you.
武当山是酒馆娼窑，我不希罕
Wudan is a whorehouse! Keep your lessons!
该说你回来早呢，还是回来晚了
You're home late, or should I say early?
你怎么还在这儿？
Why are you still here?
你杀了狗官差
You killed a policeman.
不能再待在这儿了
You should leave!
我跟你说过了
你会连累我们全家的
You'll bring ruin on my whole family.
要不是你盗走了青冥剑
They wouldn't have found me...
别人怎么会发现我在这儿？
if you hadn't stolen the sword.
你不小了
Like a little girl,
你以为拿走了青冥剑是好玩的？
you thought stealing would be fun?
我有份，你就有份
You, too, are responsible for that death.
咱俩一起走
Come with me.
要是你真成了朝廷命官的夫人
You don't want to waste your life...
你会憋死的
as the wife of some bureaucrat.
天份也埋没了
Denied your talent...
来，我们师徒两人…
As master and disciple we will rule.
我不会跟你去做江洋大盗
I'll never live as a thief!
你已经是人人捉拿的江洋大盗了
You're already a thief.
我只是想玩玩
That was just for fun.
我干嘛走，我走哪儿去？
How can I leave? Where would I go?
哪儿都行
想干什么就干什么
Wherever we want.
谁想拦我们，就杀他个痛快
We'll get rid of anyone in our way.
就连你爹也一样
Even your father.
你给我闭嘴
Shut up!
这就是江湖
It's the Giang Hu
恩恩怨怨、你死我活
fighter lifestyle... kill or be killed.
很吓人，也很刺激，是吧？
Exciting, isn't it?
对你，我已仁至义尽了
I owe you nothing.
仁至义尽的是我
Yes, you do!
收你为徒…
You are still my disciple.
是我这一辈子最得意的一件事
你以为这几年是你…
You think you've been...
在教我《武当剑法心诀》吗？
teaching me all these years from the manual?
幸亏你识字不多
You couldn't even decipher the symbols!
我依图，你依字…
I studied the diagrams.
原来你留了一手
But you hid the details!
那些字就算你知道也不能体会
You wouldn't have understood, even if I had tried to explain.
你心里明白
You know...
你的功夫就只能练到这里了
you've gone as far as you can go.
我藏而不露，也只是怕你伤心
I hid my skills so as not to hurt you.
要不是李慕白那天…
If I hadn't seen...
试出了你的功力
you fight with Li Mu Bai,
我还真不知道你瞒了我这么多
I'd still be ignorant of all you've hidden from me.
师娘
Master...
徒弟十岁起就随你秘密练功
I started learning from you in secret when I was 10.
你给了我一个江湖的梦
You enchanted me with the world of Giang Hu.
可是有一天
But...
我发现我可以击败你
once I realized I could surpass you,
你不知道我心里有多害怕
I became so frightened!
我看不到天地的边
Everything fell apart.
不知道该往哪里去
I had no one to guide me,
我又能跟随谁？
no one to learn from.
你走上了这条道
Believe me,
怕的还在后面呢
I've a lesson or two left to teach you!
剑回来了，高兴吗？
The sword is back...Are you happy?
失而复得
I admit...
才知道对它还是有依恋
getting it back makes me realize how much I'd missed it.
已经不是你的剑了
But it's not your sword anymore.
你不是说要送给贝勒爷吗？
You gave it to Sir Te.
是啊
True.
不过我恐怕还得再借用一回
But I must borrow it for one last mission.
你要让碧眼狐狸死在这把剑下
Jade Fox must die at its edge.
秀莲，你掩护那女孩儿的时候
Did you know what you were hiding...
知不知道她是谁？
when you covered for that girl?
我的责任是要把剑找回来
My job was to get the sword back,
还得顾及大家的颜面
without embarrassing anyone.
我若是把所知的都说出来
I wasn't about to ruin
不但毁了这位姑娘的一生
her life,
更要连累她爹
or her father's.
你事情处理得很漂亮
You did your job well.
剑也要回来了
只是…
But,
这女孩儿…昨夜我见着她了
this girl...I saw her last night.
我就知道你会疑心
I knew she would intrigue you.
她的心性需要约束
She needs direction...
武艺更需要导正和进一步的修练
and training.
她是官家的千金
She's an aristocrat's daughter.
不是我们这种江湖中人
She's not one of us.
慕白，这件事很快就会过去
In any case, it will all be over soon.
你会杀掉碧眼狐狸
You'll kill Fox,
她也会安安份份地去嫁人
and she'll marry.
她不是那种人
That's not for her.
她应该到武当山来做徒弟
She should come to Wudan and become a disciple.
武当山收女弟子吗？
But Wudan does not accept women.
为她…也许破个例吧
For her, they might make an exception.
如果不成，这姑娘…
If not, I'm afraid...
将来恐怕成为一条毒龙
she'll become a poisoned dragon.
这不关我们的事，她就要嫁人了
It's not our affair.
就算武当肯收她
Even if Wudan accepts her,
她丈夫…这位当朝的翰林
her husband might object.
恐怕也不会答应吧
唉！
交出了青冥剑
I thought by giving away the sword,
以为可以从此退出江湖
I could escape the Giang Hu world.
没想到又惹来了江湖上…
But the cycle of bloodshed continues.
许多新仇旧恨
我也想过平静的日子
I wish there were something more
真不知道该怎么帮你
I could do to help you.
耐心点吧！秀莲
Just be patient with me, Shu Lien.
别动！
小虎？
Lo?
小龙
Jen!
你不该来找我
You shouldn't have come.
最近你们家的屋顶…
With all the traffic...
半夜里还真热闹
on your rooftop these days...
我好不容易才能进来
it took me a while to get in here.
我不能再等了，小龙
I can't wait any longer.
我错了，我不该让你走
I was wrong to let you go.
跟我回去，回新疆你就舒展了
Come back with me. You'll be happy in the desert.
想做什么就做什么
You'll be free there.
这些日子你一直在找我？
You've been looking for me all this time?
娇龙啊，别摆弄它了
Jen...Stop playing with it.
走这么久都没事
I won't break it.
停！
半天云
It's Dark Cloud!
半天云来啦
Dark Cloud is coming!
半天云来啦…
保护小姐及夫人
Dark Cloud is coming!
快把帘子放下来
Lower the shade,
别让他们看见你
don't let them see you!
不要害怕
不要碰女人
Don't touch the women!
我说不要碰女人
走！
Let's go!
来呀…
来拿梳子
Come get your comb.
喂
你的妈妈没事，快回去
Hurry back to your mother.
她是我的，让我来
She's mine! Leave her to me!
来，梳子在这儿
Come and get it!
还我梳子
Give me back my comb!
歇手！停一下
Let's stop a moment.
还我梳子
Give it back!
你累了，你要休息
You're tired. You need rest.
你的马要喝水了，前面有水
Your horse needs water. There's a creek up here.
上次来还有水的
Well, there used to be!
你的名字？
What's your name?
我是罗小虎
I'm Lo.
汉人们都叫我“半天云”
The Hans call me Dark Cloud.
我没有那么高，也没有那么大
I'm not that tall or big,
可是我很快
but I'm quick as lightning.
来
还我梳子
My comb!
你喜欢…
If you like that arrow,
我可以做一把小弓弩给你
I can make you a bow.
打猎很管用的
Great for hunting wild chicken.
香喷喷的呱啦鸡
They're delicious.
你要吃东西了，知道吗？
You need to eat. Understand?
吃过东西，有力气
Then you'll have the strength...
我们再打一打
to fight.
好吗？
Understand?
慢慢的才会有力气，不要急
You're eating too fast. Slowly.
你的脾气很不好，这样就好了
You've got quite a temper. It's better this way...
怕死就别装汉子
You coward!
你的脾气还是不好
Still in a bad mood?
不过你说话了，告诉我你的名字
At least you're speaking. What's your name?
呸！
呸？汉人没有这种名字的
I didn't think the Hans had names like that.
别紧张
Relax.
我有你一半坏
If I had wanted to,
你现在就不是这样了
I would already have done it.
我知道你很想洗澡
You must be dying for a bath.
水源很远，路很难走
Fresh water's hard to get here.
我替你把水背来了
But I managed to bring some up.
洗好了，穿我的衣服
You can wear my clothes when you're done.
很干净的
They're clean.
放心
Don't worry.
你听我唱歌
I'll sing,
就知道我近了还是远了
so you'll know where I am.
等你洗好了，心情就好了
After the bath, you'll be calmer.
不可以再打人
No more hitting on the head!
为一把梳子，值得吗？
All this trouble for a comb?
那是我的
It's mine.
它对我来说很珍贵
It means a lot to me.
象你这样的土匪就没用
A barbarian like you wouldn't understand.
不对，我可以用它挑马蚤
Not true. I can use it to pick fleas from my horse.
告诉你，我是旗人
By the way, I'm a real Manchurian.
噢，你说的对
I'm sorry...
我猜错了，我以为你是汉人
I guessed wrong. I thought you were a Han.
把梳子还给我
Give me back my comb.
没有人可以命令我
I don't take orders from anyone.
给我
Give it back.
小的时候…
One night...
有一天夜里
when I was a boy,
我看见天上落下千万颗的星星
I saw a thousand shooting stars.
我想，它们都落到哪里去了？
I thought, "Where did they all go?"
我是个孤儿
I'm an orphan.
我就一个人去找星星
I used to look for stars alone.
我想，如果我骑马…
I thought if I rode...
到了沙漠的另一头
to the other end of the desert,
我就可以找到它的
I'd find them.
从那以后
I've been...
我就一直在大漠中奔驰
riding in the desert ever since.
后来小男孩儿变成了强盗
And so, the little boy became a fearsome bandit.
星星找不到，就抢我的梳子
He couldn't find the stars, so he stole my comb.
在大漠中
Out here,
要活着，就要不断地拼杀
you always fight for survival.
大家要联合起来
You have to be part of a gang...
才有机会活下去
to stand a chance.
你的同伴就成了自己的家
Slowly, your gang becomes your family.
那个“半天云”的名字…
All that Dark Cloud stuff is just to scare people
只是一个让人更容易活下去的迷
and make my life easier.
所以你在心里头还是个小男孩儿
So you are still that little boy
在寻找那些流星？
looking for shooting stars.
我是一个男人了
I am a man.
而且…
And now...
我已经找到最亮的一颗星了
I've found the brightest star of all.
你爸爸的人在找你
Your father's men are looking for you.
你爸爸还在找你
They're still out there, circling closer.
让他们找吧
Let them look.
他们找来找去，是我的麻烦
It is trouble for me.
你别送我回去
Don't send me back.
你自己决定吧
You must decide.
也许以后你会很烦，会不习惯…
You might get tired of this life.
你会想你的爸爸，想你的妈妈
You might begin to miss your family.
如果我们有一个女儿不见了
If it were our daughter,
我们也会找的
we'd look for her too.
我们的女儿也会想我们的
She would miss us.
小龙
Jen...
我要你做我的女人
I want you to be mine forever.
我一定会干一番事业
I will make my mark on the world.
让你的爸爸妈妈，看得起我
I will earn your parents respect.
我们有一个传说…
We have a legend.
如果谁敢从那个山上跳下来
Anyone who dares to jump from the mountain,
天神就会满足他一个愿望
God will grant his wish.
很久以前有一个人，父母病了…
Long ago, a young man's parents were ill,
他就从山上跳下去
so he jumped.
结果他没有死，一点伤都没有
He didn't die. He wasn't even hurt.
后来他漂泊到一个地方去
He floated away, far away,
再也没有回来
never to return.
他知道他的愿望实现了
He knew his wish had come true.
真心的，就会实现
If you believe, it will happen.
我问过老人们，他们说是…
The elders say,
心诚则灵
"A faithful heart makes wishes come true".
把它保存好
Keep it safe.
等我们重新相聚的时候
Return it to me...
再还给我
when we are together again.
我会
I will.
如果你不还我，我会追到你
If you don't, I'll come after you.
下一次我可不会对你这么客气了
And I won't let you off so easy.
可是我每前进一步
Wherever I went...
就有人认出我来
someone always recognized me.
我真的尽了力
I really tried.
我听说你们去了北京
Later, I heard you came to Peking.
我怕再也见不到你了
I was afraid I'd never see you again.
所以我就来了
So I came.
我不能让你嫁人
I can't let you marry.
你回去吧
Go.
小龙…
Jen...
永远永远不要回来
Don't ever come back.
就这样？
So it's over?
就这样
Yes.
小姐，好象有什么动静吧？
We heard noises.
没有，是猫
It was just a cat.
你想碧眼狐狸会出现吗？
You think Jade Fox will show up?
她一定在附近盯着
She's out there,
我料她不至于傻到让人发现
but I doubt she'll show herself.
我们得留神
We'll keep our eyes open.
她迟早会想法子…
Sooner or later,
回到她的主子身边
she'll come for the girl.
小龙！
Jen!
小龙
小龙，跟我回新疆
Jen! Come with me!
什么人？
不要拉我，放开我…
让开
小龙
没有人可以娶你
你是我的，跟我回新疆
You're mine! Come with me to the desert!
小龙，跟我回新疆
Jen! Come with me to Xin Jiang!
快告诉我！碧眼狐狸在哪里？
Tell me. Where is Jade Fox?
跟我来，快走！
Come with me. Hurry!
你真以为她会抛下一切…
You thought she'd give it all up...
跟你回新疆吗？
and go back West with you?
她是我的
She's mine.
不论她是不是你的…
Either way,
你没有命，说什么也没用
you are no good to her dead.
有鲁家跟玉家的势力盯着你
With the Gou and Yu clans
要抓你这个外地人，是很快的事
hunting you, you'll soon be in their hands.
豁出去了
I don't care anymore.
如果你真的爱她，你不会这样说
If you truly loved her, you wouldn't say that.
你难道不想再见娇龙一面吗？
Don't you want to see her again?
好吧
All right.
我手书一封，你带去武当山
I'll write you an introduction. Take it to Wudan.
在那等我消息
Wait there for news from me.
好吧
All right.
唉！看来这江湖恩怨未了
When will this end?
想拿就拿，想还就还
They take it, they put it back, they take it again.
我这里连外城的库房都不如
My home is turning into a warehouse.
进来
Come in.
讲
Speak!
玉娇龙离家出走
Jen has run away!
听说鲁爷入洞房的时候
Gou found...
新娘子不见了
the wedding chamber empty.
玉府想探贝勒爷个信儿
Governor Yu requests your assistance.
是不是愿意帮着寻找一下
说是贝勒爷江湖上认识人多…
You know the Giang Hu underworld.
传个话出去，一是容易找到
He wants to find her,
二是别出什么事儿
and keep her from harm.
贝勒爷，这事就交给我们
Sir Te, leave this to us.
不劳您费心
Don't worry.
侍候点什么？
What can I serve you?
怎么这么脏？
This cup is dirty.
打扰了
Hello.
敢问尊姓大名，怎么称呼啊？
What's your name?
姓龙
Long.
原来是龙少侠，失敬…
It's young Master Long. My apologies!
在下“冀东铁鹰爪”宋明
I'm Iron Eagle Sung
这位是我师哥“飞天豹”李云
and this is my brother in arms, Flying Cougar Li Yun.
不知道龙少侠途径怀安…
What brings you to Huai An,
要到哪儿去啊？
and where are you headed, Master Long?
哪儿好玩儿去哪儿
Anywhere there's action.
人生地不熟，我们哥儿俩…
In that case,
帮你调查调查地面儿
perhaps we could be of assistance.
用不着你们操心
Don't bother.
这位是真不懂是假不懂啊
You don't seem to understand.
不懂怎么着？
So what if I don't?
不懂有不懂的规矩
We have ways of helping you to understand.
敢问少侠跟武当派的李慕白是…
Are you related to Li Mu Bai?
手下败将
He is my defeated foe!
喝杯茶吧
Have some tea.
秀莲
Shu Lien...
我们能触摸的东西没有“永远”
The things we touch have no permanence.
师父一再的说…
My master would say...
把手握紧，里面什么也没有
there is nothing we can hold on to in this world.
把手松开，你拥有的是一切
Only by letting go can we truly possess what is real.
慕白
这世间…
不是每一件事都是虚幻的
Not everything is an illusion.
刚才你握着我的手
My hand...
你能感觉到它的真实吗？
wasn't that real?
你的手冰凉凉的
Your hand, rough...
那些练刀练出来的硬茧…
and callused from practice...
每一次我看见，都不敢触摸
All this time, I've never had the courage to touch it.
秀莲
江湖里卧虎藏龙…
Giang Hu is a world of tigers and dragons,
人心里何尝不是？
full of corruption...
刀剑里藏凶…
人情里何尝不是？
我诚心诚意的把青冥剑交出来
I tried sincerely to give it up
却带给我们更多的烦恼
but I have brought us only trouble.
压抑只会让感情更强烈
To repress one's feelings only makes them stronger.
我也阻止不了我的欲望
You're right, but I don't know what to do.
我想跟你在一起
I want to be with you...
就象这样坐着
just like this.
我反而能感觉到一种平静
It gives me a sense of peace.
客官里边请
Please follow me.
要间干净的房
I want a clean room.
房间有的是
We have plenty.
客官，吃点什么？
Your order?
花雕蒸鳜鱼、干炸头号里脊
Steamed whole cod,
溜丸子
bite-size meatballs,
丸子小一点，芡粉少一点
a little starchy, but keep the sauce light,
再来一个翅子白菜汤
shark fin soup,
二两玫瑰露，温过
mixed vegetables, and some warm wine.
客官，这得等
这要到大馆子才有
I have to order from a bigger restaurant.
那就快去呀
Hurry then.
就是他
That's him.
在下“铁臂神拳”米大彪
I am Iron Arm Mi.
路过此地
听闻有高人在此
I heard a true master has arrived.
特来请教
I have come to seek a lesson.
那在下就失礼了
You asked for it!
哼！什么铁臂神拳
What kind of Iron Arm are you?
好厉害的点穴法
You have amazing technique!
在下“花影无踪”飞刀常
I am Flying Saber.
敢问这位与江南鹤可曾认识？
Are you related to Southern Crane?
什么鸡鸭鹤？
Southern Duck?
我从来不吃两只脚的东西
I don't eat anything with two feet.
你们名字也太罗嗦，谁记得住
Who could remember such long-winded names?
你…
你说李慕白是你的手下败将
Li Mu Bai is your defeated foe,
怎么不知道江南鹤是他师父？
and you don't know his master Southern Crane?
你是哪儿的？
Who are you?
在下“凤阳山魁星五手”鲁君雄
I'm Shining Phoenix Mountain Gou.
鲁君雄…好个鲁君雄
Gou? I hate that name.
我听到你的名字就想吐
It makes me puke!
你活该倒霉姓“鲁”
Too bad you're named Gou.
要比划就先拿你开刀
You'll be the first to feel my sword today.
住手
Hold it!
你可认得江南静玄禅师？
Don't you know Monk Jing?
和尚不念经…
A monk, in a place like this?
跑到这里开荤也该教训
You need a lesson!
你到底是何人？
Who are you?
我呀…
Who am I?
我乃是…
I am...
他手里有宝剑
I am the Invincible Sword Goddess.
我乃是潇洒人间一剑仙
Armed with the incredible...
青冥宝剑胜龙泉
Green Destiny.
任凭李俞江南鹤
Be you Li or Southern Crane...
都要低头求我怜
lower your head and ask for mercy.
沙漠飞来一条龙
I am the desert dragon.
神来无影去无踪
I leave no trace.
今朝踏破峨嵋顶
Today I fly over Eu-Mei.
明日拔去武当峰
Tomorrow I'll kick over Wudan Mountain!
好言好语跟他请教
We politely asked for a friendly match,
他是一点儿规矩也没有
but she showed no respect,
出口伤人，出手伤人
and attacked us.
道上兄弟都往这儿赶哪
Everyone came by...
要教训这没规矩的小子
to teach her a lesson.
他的剑实在厉害
Her sword was just too powerful.
我游方四海
I've traveled everywhere,
从未见过如此无理之人
but never met anyone so uncivilized.
他硬说，我和他的仇家…
She kept accusing me...
“鲁君佩”是兄弟
of being Gou Jun Pei's brother.
这鲁君佩到底是什么人哪？
Who is this Gou, anyway?
是她丈夫
Her husband.
是她丈夫啊…
镖局离这儿不远
We're close to your headquarters.
是不是要回家看一看？
Go home and check in.
你们呢？
What about you?
我到附近打听一下，随后就来
I'll look around and catch up later.
也好
Not a bad idea.
我们今晚就在雄远镖局落脚
Tonight we'll get...
先睡个好觉吧
a good night's sleep at headquarters.
好
头儿回来啦
Mistress, you're back.
哟！头儿回来啦
It's you!
你们几个…家里都好吧？
How is everything here?
都安在…
Fine.
大姐这一去怎么去那么久？
You've been gone a while.
事儿赶事儿！还得走
Yes, and I leave again tomorrow.
阿伟，老婆生了？
Your wife was due?
生了个丫头
Yeah, a baby girl.
丫头好啊
Good!
能有大姐一个脚趾头，就知足了
I'll be happy if she's half as strong as you.
吴妈
Mrs. Wu...
你回来啦
You're back!
膀子还疼不疼？
How's the arm? Still sore?
好多了
Much better.
那好
怎么这一次这么久才回来呀
You've been gone so long.
吴妈，慕白今晚会来小住
Li Mu Bai is coming to stay the night.
我马上给他收拾房间
I'll go and make up his room!
俞姐姐
Sister Shu Lien...
既然是找我，就得有个样子
Here you must be in proper attire.
我只不过是求个干净衣裳
I'm just borrowing some clean clothes.
又不是来做客
I'm not staying.
你本事挺大的，不必我给你吧
I'll give them to you.
我也只是路过，想看看你，你…
I was just passing by and wondered how you were.
姐…
You, sister...
好了，祸也闯了
Look at the trouble you've caused.
也知道，道上是怎么回事了
Now you know what Giang Hu life is really like.
你来…
就是你心里真有我这个姐姐
If you think of me as your sister,
既然是这样，道理得说清楚
let me give you some sisterly advice.
可以不嫁，父母不能丢下
You can run from marriage, but not your parents.
就是他们让我嫁的
They forced me to marry!
先让爹娘放心
Go back to them first.
你与小虎的事，再看着办
Then you can decide about Lo.
你知道罗小虎…
You know about Lo?
他是一片真心
He really loves you.
你们俩的事还有商量
歇一下，跟我回北京
Come back to Peking with me.
没有商量不成的事
We'll find a solution.
他在哪里？
Where is he now?
李慕白已经安排了
Li Mu Bai has made arrangements.
李慕白？
李慕白让他去武当山了
He sent him to Wudan Mountain.
你们都是一起的
You're working together to set me up!
给我下套儿…我走
I'm leaving!
娇龙，闭嘴，你凭什么骂人
How dare you accuse us!
从一开始…
I always knew...
我就知道是你拿了青冥剑
you had stolen the sword!
我一路替你隐瞒
I've done nothing...
护着你和你的家人
but protect you and your family.
你除了蔑视我
And you've repaid me with nothing...
你拿什么来报答？
but contempt.
李慕白没有惩罚你
Li Mu Bai himself spared you,
你反而一再恶言挑衅
and all you do is insult him.
我们祈求的一点平静…
We wanted some peace...
都教你给毁了，你还不甘心？
and you've ruined it all!
这样的姊妹，不要也罢
You're no sister of mine!
我不在乎
What do I care?
朋友本来就是假的
You were never a real friend anyway.
只不过我怀疑…
But I wonder...
做我的敌人你能撑多久
how long could you last as my enemy?
把剑放下
Put the sword down!
上面有人，什么人…抓起来
娇龙
Jen!
通通出去，把门关上
Everyone out. Shut the doors.
好，说翻脸就翻脸
Fine... the friendship is over.
不准摸
Don't touch it!
那是李慕白的剑
That's Li Mu Bai's sword.
有本事来拿
Come and get it if you can.
有本事就别用宝剑
Without the Green Destiny, you are nothing.
哼！打不赢怪兵器不好
Don't be a sore loser.
去啊！随便挑
Go ahead. Take your pick.
我等着你
I'll wait.
去啊
Go ahead.
把剑给我
Give me the sword.
拿去
Take it!
住手
Stop it!
你不配用这把剑
You don't deserve the Green Destiny.
又来个教训人的，看剑
Not another lecture! On guard!
到此为止
Let's end this here.
从今以后我认剑不认人
Only the sword will settle this.
当日古寺留一步给你
I only let you go...
是要见你的本心
because I wanted to see the real you.
你们这些老江湖
What do you know...
怎么见得到本心
about a true heart?
为什么非要缠着我？
What do you want?
还是那句话，我来教你心诀
What I've always wanted, to teach you.
好吧
All right.
三招之内你能拿回青冥剑…
If you can take back the sword in three moves,
我就跟你走
I'll go with you.
剑还我
Give it back!
拜师
Kneel!
做梦
Never!
那剑就没有了
Then you have no use for the sword.
我知道那帮人…
Sooner or later...
早晚会把你逮回去的
they'd drag you back to Peking.
你爹娘是要面子的人
Your parents...
哪能容你再进家门
will never accept you again.
家有什么好？
But why go home?
既然出来了，我们就到处走走
We've gone this far, we won't stop now.
你还是我的千金小姐
You'll always be my Lady.
人生一世，不就图个痛快？
At last, we'll be our own masters.
这下子好了
We'll be happy.
我们可以做自己的主啊
That's the most important thing.
你我都是自己唯一的亲人
All we have left is each other, right?
快躺下…别乱动
Lie down and rest.
这样儿的姑娘，杀了算了
She's crazy. You should have killed her.
下不去手
I didn't have the heart.
慕白啊，也许能下得了手
Well, Li Mu Bai can do it.
你要剑…还是要我？
Is it me or the sword you want?
你中了迷香
You've been drugged.
碧眼狐狸在哪里？
Where is Jade Fox?
怎么了
What happened?
碧眼狐狸给她施了迷香
Jade Fox drugged her.
你们怎么来的？
How did you get here?
碧眼狐狸往这边走，我们跟来的
We followed Jade Fox.
小心
师娘
你的路已经到了尽头
And so you die.
你也一样
And so shall you!
是毒针
A poisoned needle!
虽然你死也不冤
You deserve to die,
徒儿不肖…我要的是玉娇龙的命
but the life I was hoping to take...was Jen's.
十年苦心
Ten years I devoted to you.
就是因为你一肚子的坏水
But you deceived me!
隐藏心诀…
You hid the manual's true meaning.
让我苦练不成
I never improved...
而你…却是剑艺精进
but your progress was limitless!
什么是毒？
You know what poison is?
一个八岁的孩子就有这种心机…
An eight-year-old girl, full of deceit.
这就是毒
That's poison!
娇龙…
Jen!
我唯一的亲…
My only family...
唯一的仇！
my only enemy...
你不能死
You can't die!
告诉我，你用的是什么毒？
Tell us what poison you used!
什么毒…
你不能死
You can't die!
解方是什么？
Tell us the antidote!
你不能让他死，李慕白不能死
You can't let Li Mu Bai die!
是九转紫阴针
She used Purple Yin...
什么？
紫阴针…毒走心脉…
Purple Yin poison. It goes straight to the heart.
一个时辰之后
静脉的血，就会开始倒流
My blood will soon reverse its flow.
我师父江南鹤…
It's the same poison
就是送命在紫阴针下
she used to kill my master.
这毒没解的
There is no antidote.
一定有解，一定能解
That can't be!
相生相克
Everything has an antithesis!
一物…
怎么可能一物不能克一物
Why not this?
我知道解方
The antidote exists.
是从师娘那儿知道的
She taught it to me.
其实药方并不难
The formula is simple,
只是很不容易配
but it takes time...
需要时间
to prepare.
相信我
Trust me.
你们救了我
As you have helped me,
让我救他吧
let me help him.
好吧，你快去
All right. Hurry.
以我的内力，顶多只有一个对时
I will hold on as long as I can.
骑我的马去，镖局里药材不少
Take my horse and go to the compound.
给吴妈看这个，她会帮你，快去！
Give this to Mrs. Wu. She'll help you. Hurry!
守住真气，我一定回来
Spare your energy. I'll be back!
有人闯进来啦
吴妈…
Where is Mrs. Wu?
住手
Stop it!
这是俞姐的，俞姐叫我来的
Shu Lien told me to show you this.
让她进来
Let her in.
慕白，守住气
Mu Bai, hold on.
给我一点希望
Give me some hope.
秀莲
Shu Lien...
别动气
Save your strength.
生命已经到了尽头
My life is departing.
我只有一息尚存
I've only one breath left.
用这口气，练神还虚吧
Use it to meditate.
解脱得道、元寂永恒
Free yourself from this world
一直是武当修练的愿望
as you have been taught.
提升这一口气
Let your soul rise to eternity
到达你这一生追求的境地
with your last breath.
别放下、浪费在我身上
Do not waste it for me.
我已经浪费了这一生
I've already wasted my whole life.
我要用这口气对你说…
I want to tell you with my last breath...
我一直深爱着你！
I have always loved you.
我宁愿游荡在你身边…
I would rather be a ghost, drifting by your side...
做七天的野鬼…
as a condemned soul...
跟随你
就算落进最黑暗的地方
than enter heaven without you.
我的爱…
Because of your love...
也不会让我成为永远的孤魂
I will never be a lonely spirit.
他走了？
He's gone?
刘师傅
Bo...
剑就托你送还贝勒府
please take this sword back to Sir Te.
去武当山
Now you must go to Wudan Mountain.
小虎在那里等着你
Lo awaits you there.
答应我
Promise me one thing.
不论你对此生的决定为何…
Whatever path you take in this life...
一定要真诚的对待自己
be true to yourself.
小龙
还记得你说的那个故事吗？
Do you remember the legend of the young man?
心诚则灵
"A faithful heart makes wishes come true."
许个愿吧，小虎
Make a wish, Lo.
一起回新疆！
To be back in the desert, together again.